Guide to the Historic Landscape Survey of Allegheny County Records, 1970-2002 AIS.2005.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Historic Landscape Survey of Allegheny County Records
1970-2002
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Historic Landscape Survey of Allegheny County (Project)
AIS.2005.01
6.25 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Pittsburgh History & Landmarks Foundation (PHLF) is a non-profit organization founded in 1964 with a mission to preserve the city's treasured and historic architecture. The Landscape Survey presents efforts by the PHLF to catalog, document, and in some cases restore some of Pittsburgh's most notable gardens and parks.
History
The Historic Landscape Survey was the result of efforts made by the Pittsburgh History & Landmarks Foundation to gather information on many of the city's most prized parks and notable private gardens. Spearheaded by landscape historian Barry Hannegan, the survey collected documents, photographs, and ownership information along with articles dating back into the nineteenth century. The articles found in this collection are copies of the originals. The survey began in the mid 1990s and still continues.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains 5 linear feet of material, which is arranged according to the nature of the content. Box 1 houses information dealing primarily with private gardens and estates. Items in Box 2 refer to Pittsburgh's public parks, recreational areas, and Phipps Conservatory. These are then broken down further to correspond with the Pittsburgh street or neighborhood where they are located. In Box 3, much of the material relates to the city's university district, large cemeteries, and religious institutions. Box 4 and 5 are miscellaneous in nature. Many of the documents found in these two boxes relate gardening and landscaping to the broader academic discipline of horticulture. The file folders found in this collection often contain two sets of dates. The earlier dates, going back as early as the turn of the century, are copied articles pertaining to a city park or specific garden design. The later date range gives the proper indication of when the survey was active.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift from the Pittsburgh History Landmarks Foundation, January 7, 2005.
Previous Citation
Historic Landscape Survey of Allegheny County Records, 1970-2002, AIS.2005.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Phipps Conservatory (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Gardens -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Landscape architecture -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Cemeteries -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Historic buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Parks -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Associations; Architecture; Hannegan, Barry; Historic Landscape Survey of Allegheny County (Project); Pittsburgh History & Landmarks Foundation; Vater, David L.
- Edgeworth: Beaver Rd., Copied Articles, 1925, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Edgeworth: Woodland Rd., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Edgeworth: Chestnut Rd., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Edgeworth: Shields Lane and Little Sewickley Creek Rd, Copied Articles, 1906, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Edgeworth: Miscellaneous, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Sewickley: Copied Articles, 1902-1931, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Sewickley: Copied Articles, 1929-1931, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Sewickley Heights: Blackburn Rd, Copied Articles, 1931, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Sewickley Heights: Pink House Rd., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Sewickley Heights: Watson Rd., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Sewickley Heights: Persimmon Rd., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Sewickley Heights: Scaife Rd., 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Sewickley Heights: Way Hollow Rd and Farm Hill, Copied Articles, 1931, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Fox Chapel: North Dr., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Fox Chapel: Fairview Rd., 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Fox Chapel: Fox Chapel Rd. and La Torella Rd., Shady Side Academy, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- McKeesport: Fifth and Renziehousen, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Wilmerding, Copied Articles and Items Pertaining to 75th Anniversary, 1890-1965, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Indiana County: Hartwood Acres, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Pleasant Hills: Arboretum and Jefferson Memorial Park, 1970-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- West Mifflin: Kennywood Park, Copied Articles, 1899-1910, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- McCandless Township: North Park, 1970-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bethel Township: South Park, 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Miscellaneous Park Articles, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Vandergrift, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Allegheny River Boulevard, 1931-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Allegheny county Parks: Copied Articles, Photos, Maps, Correspondence, 1949, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Allegheny County Parks Comprehensive Master Plan: Inventory and Analysis Report, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Highland Park, 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Frick Park, 1927-2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Riverview, 1940-1996 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Schenley Park, 1896-1996 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Grandview Park, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Holiday Park, 1886, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Friendship Park, (Maps, 1996 1896, 1912) (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Arsenal Park, (Maps and Copied Articles, 1996 1896-1935) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- North Side Commons, (Maps and Copied Articles, 1996 1896-1935) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Herron Hill Park, (Copied Articles and Photographs, undated), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ennis Park, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Ober Park, (Copied Photographs, 1996 1908-1913) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sheraden Park, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Snyder Park, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Leslie Park, (Copied Photographs, 1996-2001 1910) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- McKinley Park, (Copied Articles, Undated), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- McBride Park, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Second Avenue Park, (Copied Articles, Undated), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Olympia Park, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Westinghouse Park, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Curto Park Meeting Minutes, Correspondence and Copied Articles, 1934-2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Phipps Conservatory, (Copied Articles, Undated), 1898-1937, 1993-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15-18)
- West End Park, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
- Pittsburgh Parks Miscellaneous Copied Articles and Writings, 1898-1998 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
- Allegheny Cemetery, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Homewood Cemetery, 1994-1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Uniondale Cemetery, 1984-1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Chatham Village, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Temple Sinai, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Chatham College, Mellon Residence, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- 7009 Penn Avenue, Greenlawn, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- 5325 Wilkins Avenue (Box 2, Folder 30)
- 4875 Ellsworth Avenue, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- 1200 Chislett St., 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Herbert Avenue, Westcliff, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Penn Avenue, Edgehill, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Forbes Avenue, The Maples, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- 5090 Warrick Terrace, The Heinz House, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Warrick Terrace, Grandview, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- North Highland, at Bunker Hill, Senator William Finn's Former Home, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- 400 North Negley, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- 116 Woodland Rd., 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Fifth Avenue and Woodland Rd, The Greystone, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- 5045 Fifth Avenue, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- 623 Pitcairn Place (Includes Copied Articles), 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- 7010 Penn Avenue, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- 5360 Forbes Avenue (Includes Copied Articles), 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- 206 Gladstone, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Beechwood Boulevard, Lyndhurst, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- 1085 Shady Ave., 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- 1047 Shady Ave., 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- 1251 North Negley Avenue, Baywood (Includes Copied Articles and Photos), 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Fifth Avenue at Bigelow, Schenley Hotel, William Pitt Union, Undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Bigelow Boulevard at Beechwood Boulevard, Undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Oak St. at West Bellevue Avenue, The Grotto of the Holy Family Friary, Undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Duquesne University, Priests' Garden, Undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Wakefield St, South Oakland, Undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
- 67 17th St., Saint Patrick's Friary, Undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
- 1326 East Ohio St., Saint Nicholas Church, Undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Forbes and Bellefield Avenue, Board of Education Courtyard, Undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
- 5700 Bunker Hill, Highland House Apt. Photos, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 579 Briar Cliff (Includes Copied Articles and Photos), 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- 6500 Fifth Avenue (Mellon Park) Copied Blueprints, Notes, Articles, Correspondence, Management Plan, 1980-1999 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
- Rhode Island Designed Landscape Survey - Drafts, 1887-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6-10)
- Historic Design Landscape of Syracuse NY, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Georgia Landscape Survey Material, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- National Historic Landmark Nomination: Meridian Hill Park, Washington, DC, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Indiana Landscape Material, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Rochester, NY Landscape Material, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Historic Ohio Inventory: Question and Answer, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Maine Survey of Landscapes, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Pennsylvania Historic Resource Survey Form, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
- Landscape Survey Form: Instruction Booklet, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Garden Literature Conference, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Mt. Vernon Estate, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Historic Landscape Resource Manual, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Horticultural Academic Listings, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- National Park Service Publications, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- National Association for Olmstead Park, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Design Competition, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Dr. Barry Hannegan and David L. Vater Correspondence, 1995-2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Pittsburgh Historic Landmark Photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Historic Landmark Negative, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Pittsburgh Landmark Negative, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- 18th Street Landscaping, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Highland Park Sculptures, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Olmsted Articles and Material, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- 1909 Pittsburgh Survey (Copied), Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Olmsted Jr. City Planning Prints and Copied Articles, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Landscape Architecture Design and Correspondence Material, Copied Articles, Undated, 1994-1998 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- League of Women Voters, Citizens Education Fund, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Steven J. Hoffman, Mt. Lebanon Research Paper, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Copied Articles of Phipps and Additional Private Conservatories, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Homestead Park, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Public Buildings and Grounds, Copied Photos, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Garden and Forest Magazine, Selected Articles, 1889-1891 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Charles Schwab Architectural Record, Copied Article, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Pittsburgh Garden Tour Articles, Notes, and Releases, (Copied Articles)-, 1903 1996 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Recreational Sites and Copied Articles, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Early Garden Items and Copied Articles, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Topics on Urban Parks and Cleanup, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Historic Landscape Preservation, 1994-1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Landscape History Collaborative, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Archives of American Gardens, Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Catalogue of Landscape Records and Newsletters, 1987-1998 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Penn Avenue and 7th Street, Downtown, Pittsburgh (Labyrinth or maze), c 1990 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Garden Conservancy Tour, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- 5036 Amberson Place, Shadyside, Pittsburgh (Janet Krieger's Garden), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- 303 Le Roi Road, Point Breese, Pittsburgh (Walter and Irene Jacob's Garden), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- 5901 Braeburn Place, Shadyside, Pittsburgh (Tim and Audrey Hillman Fisher's Garden), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 31)